Hello everyone, I'm a netizen who has been lurking online for over a decade.
I'm known as Pashoushusheng.
The reason I've surfaced today is quite unexpected.
It's because
I've recently been honored to be at the center of a controversy.
And yet, I've somehow managed to come out of it unscathed.
I feel a bit like I've survived a disaster.
As a loyal audience member of both parties involved,
I've witnessed the entire controversy unfold.
I hope to provide an objective account of the events
for those who are unclear about the situation.
As the saying goes, understanding the cause and effect
is essential to determine who is right or wrong,
and most importantly, what we should do.
Finally,
I also want to share some thoughts I've kept in my heart for a long time.
Please hear me out.
Thank you all.
First, let me briefly introduce myself.
Thank you.
On Tieba and Weibo, my ID is Xuanwuyisi.
I've been a viewer of Luo Xiaohei for over a decade.
Their spin-off comic, Lanxi Town,
transitioned to a paid model for the last three episodes.
To this day, I've purchased every episode without hesitation.
I've also bought their physical books.
I'm also one of the earliest followers of Black Myth: Wukong.
When they opened pre-orders recently,
I immediately purchased their physical deluxe edition.
And I pre-ordered the digital standard edition on PS5.
Regarding this controversy,
it started with the main artist of Luo Xiaohei's spin-off comic, Lanxi Town,
Sun Gua,
who reposted rumors about the main creators of Black Myth: Wukong on Weibo.
She accused the early promotion of Black Myth: Wukong of insulting women,
but then frantically whitewashing before its release.
I had seen this Douban post a long time ago.
It's full of distortions and lies,
truly malicious.
Of course, I'll explain in detail later
how this post spreads rumors.
But for the sake of narrative,
I'll put it aside for now.
So, I pointed out in the comments,
to carefully look at the so-called evidence in the post.
It's impossible to accuse Game Science so maliciously.
Vulgarity is vulgarity,
but you can't forcefully label them as insulting women.
Game Science,
is vulgar, but
you can't forcefully label them as insulting women.
As soon as my comment was posted,
some people started mocking me.
For those who weren't too excessive,
I made some slightly sarcastic responses.
But after a few exchanges,
they started cursing at me,
very viciously.
Since there was no reasoning with them,
I could only choose to respect others' fate, etc.
Sun Gua's response.
But then I thought,
I've been following Luo Xiaohei for so many years,
I don't know what kind of character their company has.
Their employees also joke around with each other on Weibo,
sometimes even drawing some erotic pictures.
How could they believe such baseless rumors?
Sure enough,
I flipped through Sun Gua's photo album a bit,
and found two erotic pictures.
After looking at them a few times,
I posted these two pictures in the comment section.
And I tried to make up for Sun Gua,
asking if she had been hacked.
Such an open person before,
how could she believe such baseless rumors?
Sure enough,
someone came to over-interpret me again.
I responded a bit,
but at this time, Sun Gua seemed to have finished work,
and as expected, she started to get angry at me.
Because her temper was always bad before,
I hadn't said a few words to her,
and I was blocked by her.
Now, those who cursed me in that comment section,
and those who reposted to curse me,
I couldn't retort anymore.
I could only shrug,
and do my own thing.
This matter passed after a few days,
and I was quite excited.
After all, it was the first time I was cursed like this,
and cursed so badly.
But suddenly, this matter flared up again.
Because Luo Xiaohei is after all a classic work of Chinese 2D animation,
with an audience distributed across all sectors of society.
Among them, there are some who followed it since childhood and have now gradually joined the workforce.
So there are some audience members
who are self-media.
They saw what Sun Gua posted on her Weibo,
and spread this matter.
Not only that,
they also did a little digging,
and found that in the Luo Xiaohei team,
other creators also had some similar inappropriate remarks.
This matter became a bit serious.
And Sun Gua's account is not a personal account,
she has actually participated in the promotion of Luo Xiaohei,
and in her Weibo introduction,
she has her company's name.
It's impossible to say that during the promotion,
you circle out each of your employees on Weibo,
and when something happens,
you just say it's a personal remark and that's it.
This is a bit of a double standard, isn't it?
So, everyone had to go to Sun Gua's boss
to demand an explanation.
Not only does Black Myth: Wukong
need such an explanation,
but Luo Xiaohei's side must also clarify their stance.
Otherwise, they will also suffer a lot of adverse effects.
Soon, a large number of people angered by Sun Gua
went to find Luo Xiaohei's director, MTJJ.
Some of the angrier ones
even threatened him,
saying that they would retaliate against Luo Xiaohei
when promoting the second part in the future.
Among these people, there are undoubtedly
some who are indeed fans of Black Myth: Wukong,
but it cannot be ruled out that some are deliberately fanning the flames,
hoping for both sides to fight.
Under the crazy bombardment of messages,
MTJJ posted a Weibo with over a thousand words,
making the first wave of response.
Its main content is too long,
I'll summarize it for everyone here.
First, it distanced itself from the rumors slandering Black Myth: Wukong,
a bit sarcastically,
and said that what Sun Gua said were personal remarks,
he couldn't manage them at all.
But under such pressure from everyone,
he had to criticize Sun Gua,
and asked her to shut up immediately.
Additionally, the remarks of the main creators of Black Myth: Wukong from years ago,
he said were just bawdy jokes,
but I feel he was a bit sarcastic.
He himself admitted
that he had told many bawdy jokes before,
but back then, no one was stirring up trouble,
because the online atmosphere was very relaxed at that time.
Now, if he says it again,
he feels it's just asking for trouble.
And he also said,
if being disliked for telling bawdy jokes,
then one should unconditionally bear the consequences.
Finally, perhaps out of protecting his own work,
he was a bit scared,
and he sharply retaliated against
those who demanded an explanation from him
and those who threatened him with Luo Xiaohei's second part.
And he even threatened to go after Game Science.
At this time, how did Sun Gua respond?
As shown in the picture,
interestingly,
later, someone found that she was a different person on Twitter,
very patient,
very friendly,
very understanding.
I don't want to make any malicious speculations about her here,
I just want a sincere apology from her,
after all, she is not incapable of apologizing, right?
MTJJ's response,
regardless of his sarcastic tone,
in the situation where Sun Gua was spreading rumors and was in the wrong,
he still used the Spring and Autumn Annals style to support the rumor-monger.
I don't know if he was confused between right and wrong or unaware of the facts at that time.
Clearly, Sun Gua's actions were detrimental to Game Science first,
but he, in the guise of a victim,
threatened to go after Game Science.
I can't help but ask,
if someone demanding an explanation from him is wrong,
then is it right for him to go after Game Science?
Some people even praised him,
saying he has a sense of responsibility and reason,
but in fact, more people were angered by him.
So, a large amount of MTJJ's past misdeeds were dug up,
his bawdy jokes from back then were even more vulgar than Game Science's
from back then,
some were clearly bawdy jokes aimed at women.
Since he thinks Game Science should be held accountable for their past remarks,
then he should bear even greater consequences for his own more serious remarks.
As he said himself,
he has no temper at all.
The next morning,
he couldn't withstand the pressure and responded again,
saying he was too young,
too naive,
and deserved to be targeted.
He also approved of Game Science's cold handling of public relations,
and gave a simple explanation for some of his own past misdeeds.
He also said he would manage himself well,
and focus on creation.
Up to this point,
I thought the controversy could finally come to an end.
But someone found out
that he quietly deleted his past misdeeds,
and there were also many people deliberately distorting the facts,
inciting conflicts,
fanning the flames,
fanning the flames on both sides.
So MTJJ had to come out for the third time to make a statement,
this time he lowered his stance even more,
but he still refused to directly address the root cause of the incident,
that is, the rumor about Black Myth: Wukong,
the rumor reposted by Sun Gua.
Sun Gua also had to come out to apologize,
but while saying she would mute herself,
she closed the comment section.
Up to this point,
this incident can finally come to an end, right?
Some impatient netizens might be anxious,
what rumor did Sun Gua repost?
What's the story behind Black Myth: Wukong's own controversy?
Next, I will explain this matter clearly to everyone.
The rumor entangling Black Myth: Wukong and Game Science
has been around for a long time.
Every time Black Myth: Wukong trends on the hot search,
you can see a small group of people saying,
Black Myth: Wukong doesn't need female players,
the main creators of Black Myth: Wukong insult women.
Although these accusations haven't affected
the overall affirmation and expectation of the game's quality,
every time I see these remarks, I feel a sense of frustration,
like seeing a cockroach running in after a big cleanup.
If you ask them what these accusations are based on,
they will most likely give you
this Douban article reposted by Sun Gua.
The so-called evidence in this article includes:
Before the predecessor of Game Science, the Douzhan Shen production team left,
they made a self-deprecating MV,
saying that after leaving Tencent,
their team members would have to engage in the pornographic industry.
And when Game Science was first established,
they used self-deprecating jokes to recruit employees.
When Black Myth: Wukong released its first promotional video,
the main planner, Feng Ji, posted on Weibo using self-deprecating jokes
and thanked everyone for their support.
The technical artist also discussed in the Zhihu comment section
the snake spirit NPC image in Black Myth: Wukong
and briefly talked about the fetish for snake necks.
Years ago, the main artist of Black Myth: Wukong, Yang Qi, wrote an article saying
they don't need female players for reverse motivation,
reverse motivation, and the logo of Game Science looks like sperm.
After reading it, it's quite clear,
just browse through
the so-called evidence listed in this article,
it's not hard to see
the core members of Game Science
indeed made some remarks mixed with bawdy jokes,
but without exception,
they were all self-deprecating,
never directly making vulgar jokes about any woman.
This is why I said to Sun Gua,
you can say they are vulgar,
but they have no malice, right?
Others make self-deprecating jokes,
and you insist on saying they are talking about you,
isn't that self-inflicted humiliation?
how can you blame others?
Ah, at this point, someone might say,
what about the recruitment advertisement with "fat people die quickly"
and "forced orgasm"?
I was offended.
Then I would ask you to look carefully,
there are many words under the picture,
the words are what Game Science really wants to express.
They are just saying that Game Science highly values the health of its employees
and encourages them to exercise,
and they also promote a very advanced concept,
that is, making games,
you must first make yourself happy,
before you can release the product for sale.
And the so-called "no need for female players for reverse motivation",
does it mean they don't welcome female players to play their games?
In fact, just carefully read
the paragraph they excerpted in this article,
they excerpted quite detailedly,
we can see
what Yang Qi actually meant here is
he doesn't need to promote that his game has many female players
to attract those who want to pick up girls,
thereby increasing the popularity and revenue of his game.
He is actually opposing this kind of objectification of women
in promotional concepts and marketing strategies.
He insists on using the hard power of his game to attract players,
isn't this the noble pursuit of an artist?
After reading it, I can only say
admirable.
Some people question whether Yang Qi's article
is promoting stereotypical views of women,
then I would ask everyone to open their eyes and see clearly,
the first paragraph here clearly states that most female players,
Yang Qi did not deny the existence of
a small number of female players as their audience,
he is just describing the majority situation here.
If it's said to this point,
you still insist that he
is a stereotypical view,
then I have to say you are making unreasonable accusations.
For example, I can go to the female section to see female comics,
female players can also come to play games made for men,
no one is stopping them,
right?
Finally, does the logo of Game Science really look like sperm?
I'll leave it to everyone to judge,
I just say,
if your mind is full of a certain thing,
then you will easily see everything
as that thing.
And even if it is sperm, so what?
Who isn't developed from a fertilized egg?
Is there anyone now who is developed from an unfertilized egg
through parthenogenesis into a human?
It doesn't exist, right?
In fact,
those who are slandered and insulted by these rumor-mongers
are not only Game Science and Black Myth: Wukong,
many players have also been unreasonably insulted by them,
including me,
and even some female players
have been viciously cursed by them.
There's also an interesting fact,
Black Myth: Wukong has a Tieba,
the admin of this Tieba posted a thread at the end of last year
to debunk the rumors,
but this post did not spread beyond the Tieba,
classic debunking, no one saw it.
After such a long period of continuous slander,
many people have become defenders of Black Myth: Wukong,
if you go to argue with those rumor-mongers,
you will often receive very nasty curses,
for example, you can see the screenshot records above.
So how can MTJJ say that
if you are disliked for telling bawdy jokes,
there's no reason to argue,
you can only bear it yourself?
Why so many people are extremely angry at his words,
the reason is very obvious,
what we suffer is not just being disliked,
we suffer long-term humiliation and bottomless oppression.
It's a pity that
our anger
did not vent to those rumor-mongers,
but was all taken by MTJJ,
this is really unreasonable,
after all, seeking a hammer and getting a hammer,
and those who dug up his old accounts,
most of them just posted what he said back then,
asking if there's a problem,
should it be cursed,
no one went to curse him in such a vulgar and obscene way,
it can be said that they gave MTJJ a lot of face,
but there are also some friends who noticed,
what's going on here?
This matter
starts with the well-known foreign game media IGN.
The IGN here is the foreign IGN,
it has a little relationship with the domestic IGN China,
but they are not subordinate to each other.
IGN published a media commentary,
criticizing Game Science for insulting women,
the evidence they provided is the content in this Douban post,
and through their biased translation,
they distorted the original meaning of Yang Qi and Feng Ji,
adding oil and vinegar.
The content of this article is very sensitive,
so I can't post it here,
so I can only describe its content here.
They also said in the article
that they found several women who claimed to be engaged in the game industry in China,
anonymously complaining about the gender discrimination they suffered,
but only their one-sided words,
no evidence was provided.
Additionally,
this article also took the opportunity to denigrate our country's regime, right?
Since they want to stir the anti-China muddy water,
don't blame me for having too many associations.
Isn't it just hiring actors as witnesses?
The several women they invited claimed to be engaged in the game industry in China,
who knows where they found these extras?
Even whether they found these few people,
I have to put a question mark.
This rumor article by foreign media, although it cannot be confirmed,
the domestic rumor-mongers are indeed related to foreign forces,
but the content of their materials highly overlaps,
isn't this a bit too coincidental?
It's not groundless,
but a very reasonable question.
Recently,
foreign players have been supporting Black Myth: Wukong in various ways
to express their resistance to this kind of black society forces.
Speaking of this,
the feud between Luo Xiaohei and Black Myth: Wukong,
I think it's basically clear,
at least it's clear about the part I know.
If you ask me what I think about this matter,
I just want to say that extremists should go die.
After all, I've been watching Luo Xiaohei for over a decade,
and Black Myth: Wukong,
I've been following them since their first public appearance until now,
any harm to either side will make me very angry.
MTJJ is unwise,
while Game Science is as still as a mirror,
truly has great wisdom.
It's no wonder that MTJJ worked in a big company before.
MTJJ said
he wanted to end this dispute with an article,
this is because of his own double standards and sarcastic attitude towards employees,
and after coming out three times,
I don't think he found where his problem lies,
this makes me extremely disappointed in him.
But in the end, there's no smoke without fire,
some people spread rumors,
some people fan the flames,
those who maliciously set the rhythm for Black Myth: Wukong,
shouldn't they be the ones to receive the public's anger?
But what we see is
these people are still at large,
I am very angry about this reality,
but I can't do anything about it.
I actually tried to use the opportunity of MTJJ's apology
to direct the anger towards those rumor-mongers,
and not let them hide behind MTJJ and laugh anymore.
But unfortunately, MTJJ's sarcasm is too high,
he directly controlled the entire forum,
must first attack that sarcastic follower.
What can I say?
Some people accuse me of stirring up trouble,
well,
I can't accept this.
Because from the beginning, everyone can see,
I've been putting out fires for MTJJ and Sun Gua.
Some people say I'm a victim,
I also don't accept it.
Although Sun Gua
did repost my remarks to her homepage,
but I actually welcome her doing so.
Because only open discussion is beneficial to clarify the truth,
make it clear.
Her blocking me
can only prove that she is in the wrong.
This wave of digging up old accounts is not only a great reversal drama,
but also evokes my memories.
Next is what I call the long-buried truth in my heart.
I am a person who is not socially anxious but very self-enclosed.
The internet has been my spiritual haven since a long time ago.
I have learned a lot of knowledge here,
seen all kinds of witty and humorous brainstorms,
admired the extraordinary skills of people from all over the world.
I have gained a lot of happiness,
and also gained a lot of strength
to face various difficulties in real life.
But what is the internet like now?
I see more and more prejudice,
more and more baseless accusations,
more and more people have to wear armor,
wear thicker and thicker armor,
but still receive more and more curses.
The past golden age obviously can't come back overnight,
but I still want to regain
the right to breathe freely on the internet.
To return to the past,
I think we must unite to resist those extremists.
This matter
must be the joint effort of everyone who participates in the internet
to achieve.
This time, we used magic to defeat magic,
which is indeed satisfying,
but it accelerates the deterioration of the internet atmosphere.
As MTJJ himself said,
making something out of nothing and escalating things
is indeed despicable,
but on the current internet,
this trick is really effective.
I sincerely call for us to return to reason,
return to kindness,
return to tolerance.
Actually, up to this point,
I think it can end,
but some people might ask,
what is my attitude towards gender equality?
So I'll add another paragraph.
My attitude is that since 1921 until now,
since the founding of New China until now,
we have been supporting women's equality in practice,
women participating in labor and social activities,
the slogan that "women can hold up half the sky" has been passed down to this day.
We once had excellent female tractor drivers,
excellent female workers,
excellent female scientists,
and now there are still countless excellent women
realizing their own value in various industries,
contributing their own strength to the progress of society.
What I support is the true gender equality behind this great cause.
Take myself as an example,
because of the major I studied, I am surrounded by women who are more excellent than me.
If I had any gender discrimination,
I would have been so angry that I would have died young long ago.
Gender equality,
in my understanding,
is to make gender irrelevant when it's irrelevant to the matter,
not a topic of discussion,
no one talks about
whether you are male or female,
you work more and get more,
you work less and get less,
the standards are the same,
the rules are the same.
And when things are related to gender,
everyone acknowledges the objective differences between the two sexes,
everyone complements each other's strengths,
helps each other,
with these as the standard,
I would like to ask everyone to think,
where in the world is gender equality done better than here?
Of course, our reality is still some distance away from true gender equality,
but gender equality is not achieved by unreasonable demands occupying three points,
reasonable demands not letting go, and making trouble out of nothing.
Some people,
they shout equality in their mouths,
but in fact, they want privileges.
If these thugs get their way,
those women who achieve success through their own efforts,
aren't they the biggest victims?
I absolutely do not allow such things to happen.
Thank you all.